Hi, I'm Sandra, from HEARa.
Welcome to Day 8
of our 10 day Lipreading Challenge,
designed to help you develop
and practice your lipreading skills.
Hearing loss can have a
profound impact on your life.
It touches every interaction.
It can affect your career,
your relationships,
and your happiness.
Join me to explore tips and tricks
on this YouTube channel
to bring confidence and clarity
to relationships in all areas of your life.
Today we're going to learn
about the TH sound.
To make this sound,
the tongue is placed between the teeth,
Watch the word “TEETH" again.
Teeth.
This sound is relatively easy
to see, especially when
it's at the beginning of the word.
Watch this:
THUMB
For our lipreading practice today,
I'm going to say the sentences
three times.
First, silently; then, out
loud; and then, silently again.
There's a couple things
I want you to keep in mind
for the practice today.
The first thing is that the first time you see the sentence,
try and stay relaxed.
Look for any word or words
that have TH in them,
and see if you recognize
any other words.
Don't try for every single word.
The second thing
is that you should try
and commit the sentences
to memory somewhat,
because you'll be seeing them again.
Are you ready?
Number 1
The sentence was:
The third month of the year is March.
Here it is again:
Number 2
The sentence was:
That's *MY* toothbrush!
Here it is again:
Number 3
The sentence was:
I thought it was this Thursday.
Here it is again:
Number 4
The sentence was:
Warm weather makes me thirsty.
Here it is again:
Number 5
The sentence was:
Thank you for thinking of me.
Here it is again:
Number 6
The sentence was:
My birthday is on the 5th of the month.
Here it is again:
Number 7
The sentence was:
Don't bother with that!
Here it is again:
Number 8
The sentence was:
Their mother is very thoughtful.
Here it is again:
Number 9
The sentence was:
We have a thousand reasons to give thanks.
Here it is again:
Number 10
The sentence was:
I wish you health, wealth, and happiness.
Here it is again:
Okay, now I'm going to randomly pick
five of those sentences
and say them silently.
If you can recognize and remember
the sentences,
you are lipreading!
As always, the answers are written below.
Are you ready?
Sentence A
Sentence B
Sentence C
Sentence D
Sentence E (this is the last one).
For the last two days in the challenge,
I've asked you to remember
the sentences.
There are many links between memory and hearing.
I've written a blog article on this topic,
and I'll link to it below
in the description section.
But today, I want to talk specifically
about working memory.
You use working memory,
for example, when you hear a phone number
and you want to hold on to it
for a little while until
you can find a pen to write it down.
Or if you're following a recipe,
and you have to remember:
half a cup of sugar, half a cup of sugar.
When you partly hear something,
maybe part of a word
or part of one word
and part of another word,
you have to hold on to that fragment
with your auditory working memory.
You hold on to that fragment
so that you can do an internal database search
in your own mind
to find something that fits.
So you're thinking,
what does that sound like?
You may have noticed
that sometimes when you don't hear clearly,
if you have a moment
to think about it
then you can figure it out.
And that's because
of that database search.
Your working memory has to be strong enough
to hold on to these fragments.
By the way,
you can strengthen
your auditory working memory
through auditory training programs,
which is another passion of mine.
This kind of memory work is heavy in terms of
consuming brain resources.
And if you're having to do this
while also listening, it's going to be hard
to do anything else,
like smile and be witty.
So your facial expression
might look something more like this.
It can be exhausting.
I mention this because it's important to be aware
that listening is hard work,
especially if you have underamplified
or untreated hearing loss.
But even with hearing aids,
you're totally multitasking
when you're listening
and remembering
and reading lips
and trying to
separate the voices from the background noise.
Lipreading and hearing aids
are another two for one.
Both hearing aids and lipreading
can support you.
It's almost like having a hard drive
with two databases in it:
a database for what it sounds like,
and another database for what it looks like.
So if you have hearing aids
without lip reading or vice versa,
it's almost like having a smaller hard drive.
It takes time and energy
on many levels
to invest in your lip reading skills,
or technology, if you need technology.
I just want to acknowledge that,
because it may seem daunting.
It's worth the effort
because communication
is at the heart of connecting to other people.
And through this lip reading challenge,
I'm trying to show you places
where you can put your effort
to make things better.
That's it for today!
I hope it was helpful.
Comments are always welcome.
Please Like, Subscribe, and share with others.
I'll see you tomorrow for Day 9!
Bye!